Finding Aid for Office of University Audits (University of Michigan) records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Office of University Audits (University of Michigan) records 1947-2012
University of Michigan. Office of University Audits.
352 MB online
18 linear feet
2014116 Bimu 2
The record group of the University Audits Office consists of reports of internal and external auditors, and files documenting the amendments of Standard Practice Guide provisions.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was transferred from the Office of University Audits (donor no. 6936 ) in December 2012 and May 2013.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Office of University Audits records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Office of University Audits record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 5-10
Executive Officers Records -- Boxes 10-18
Early on, the financial duties of the University were split between the Treasurer and the Secretary and although the State Auditor General audited funds transferred to the University from the state, it was not until 1910 that external auditors were hired to evaluate the university's annual financial statement. Prior to that date, a faculty member (such as mining engineering professor, W. H. Pettee) was commissioned to audit the statements annually.
Beginning in 1910, firms such as Price Waterhouse and Co., Ernst & Ernst and Peat, Marwick, Mitchell & Co. were hired to evaluate the accuracy of the University's financial statements and recommend financial control practices that would help prevent fraud and increase the reliability of reporting. Eventually, it became clear that the University needed in-house auditing expertise to ensure the responsible stewardship of public monies. In June 1952, the Regents amended Section 3.01 of their bylaws, concerning the Vice-President in Charge of Business and Finance, to hold that periodical internal audits of all University units would be part of the Vice-President's duties. The Internal Audit program was placed under the direction Assistant Controller Byron Green, within the University's Business Office. The office was to make periodic reports to the Board of Regents regarding the individual units examined.
In 1964 Harold Bell was named Director of the Office of Management Services and he supervised the Internal Audit Department. This office was responsible for testing compliance with established University policies and procedures and for determining whether the system of internal controls over financial transactions was adequate. After Harold Bell resigned to become Comptroller of the University of Chicago in 1966, A. B. Hicks was appointed Director of University Audits and the name of the unit was changed to University Audits, the name it holds in 2013. It is charged with coordinating responsibility for outside auditors -- federal, state and professional -- in addition to performing the internal audit function.
Another important function of University Audits is to maintain the Standard Practice Guide (SPG), the primary compilation of university policies and procedures. Originally, "Standard Practice Bulletins" were circulated only to university officials in the Business Office, such as the controller, chief accountant, purchasing agent, and cashier. These bulletins were numbered consecutively, beginning with number one on March 15, 1946 relating to the organization of the Fresh Air Camp. The 11th Bulletin on August 1, 1947 held that official notices distributed to all deans, directors and department heads affecting business and finance activities should be issued from the Office of the Vice President in Charge of Business and Finance. This was the birth of the distribution of memoranda to a circulation list which is sometimes known as the 3D's (Deans, Directors and Department Heads).
In 1968, Director of University Audits A. B. Hicks proposed a University-wide policy and procedure guide that would draw together existing policy and procedure material from the Standard Practice Bulletins and 3D memoranda into a loose-leaf format which could be maintained and appropriately indexed. University Audits was tasked with maintaining, indexing and annually updating the manual.
As the university became more complex and more offices maintained copies of the growing SPG binders, the work of maintaining the binders became more difficult. The desire for a central authoritative policy source that could be inexpensively maintained led University Audits to push for the implementation of the SPG Online in 1996. It consisted of individual .PDF files for each SPG section -- an innovative approach for its time. The original URL for the SPG Online was http://www.umich.edu/~spgonlin, in 2013 it is located at http://spg.umich.edu.
University Audits Leadership
1948-1957 Byron Green, Assistant Controller
1958-1964 Harold Bell, Assistant Controller
1964-1966 Harold Bell, ,Director of the Office of Management Services
1966-1981 A.B. Hicks, Director of University Audits
1982-1999 Carl R. Smith,Director of University Audits
1999-2004 Robert Moenart, Executive Director of University Audits
2004-2012 Carol F. Senneff, Executive Director of University Audits
2012- Jeff Moelich, Executive Director of University Audits
The University Audits record group is divided into three series: Unit Audit Reports; External Audits; and Standard Practice Guide.
The University Audits record group consists of reports of internal and external auditors, and files documenting the amendments of Standard Practice Guide provisions.
Digital Processing Note
In preparing digital materials for long-term preservation and access, the Bentley Historical Library adheres to professional best practices and standards to ensure the authenticity, integrity, and security of material. For more information on the library's digital processing procedures and policies, please see http://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/handle/2027.42/93344. Content may be available as individual files or a ZIP archives containing multiple files.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Office of University Audits.; University of Michigan--Administration.
- Unit Audit Reports
  The Unit Audit Reports series, 1953-2004 (9.5 linear feet), consist of audits conducted by University Audits staff. Initially, the audits primarily related to units that provided fee-based goods or services such as WUOM, WFUM-TV, Radrick Farms Golf Course, Student Publications, and ICA Summer Camps and Clinics. The William W. Cook Trust was also regularly audited. As the University started to computerize its recordkeeping, auditors were also tasked with evaluating the adequacy of the financial controls for the new accounting systems. Other topics that they reviewed include the control of patient confidentiality, and the Y2K computer conversions. Audit reports were initially unnumbered, but beginning in 1969 were numbered consecutively, with the first digit of the identifier corresponding to the last digit of the fiscal year of the audit. Since numbers were reused a decade later in some cases, two different audits could have the same identifier. They are arranged in order by identifier, which usually corresponds to their chronological order. There is an index of the units audited for the period 1982-2003 which is in the first folder of Box 1.
  - Indices to reports 1982-2003 (Box 1)
  - Unnumbered audit reports 1953-1978, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Reports 0-101 -- 0-132 1969-1971, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Reports 1-101 -- 1-151 1970-1972, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Reports 2-101 -- 2-159 1971-1973, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Reports 3-100 -- 3-901 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Reports 4-100 -- 4-901 1973-1975, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Reports 5-101 -- 5-901 1974-1976, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Reports 6-100 -- 6-900 1975-1977, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Reports 7-101 -- 7-900 1976-1978, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Reports 8-101 -- 8-115 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - Reports 8-116 -- 8-900 1977-1978, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Reports 9-101 -- 9-900 1978-1980, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Reports 10-101 -- 10-900 1979-1982, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Reports 1-101 -- 1-140 1980-1981, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Reports 1-141 -- 1-192 1981-1982, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Reports 2-101 -- 2-506 1981-1986, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Reports 3-101 -- 3-901 1982-1984, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Reports PW-001 -- PW-003 and 4-101 -- 4-105 1983-1984 (Box 4)
  - Reports 4-106 -- 4-900 1983-1987, 5 folders (Box 5)
    [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2018 ]
  - Reports 5-101 -- 5-900 1984-1987, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Reports 6-101 -- 6-144 1985-1988, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Reports 6-145 -- 6-900 1986-1988, 2 folders (Box 6)
    [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2023 ]
  - Reports 7-101 -- 7-502 1986-1990, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Reports 8-101 -- 8-146 1987-1993, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Reports 9-101 -- 9-132 1988-1993, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Reports 9-133 -- 9-143 1989-1999 (Box 7)
    [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2026 ]
  - Reports 0-101 -- 0-129 1989-1993, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Reports 1-101 -- 1-139 1990-1993, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Reports 2-101 -- 2-137 1991-1994, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Reports 3-101 -- 3-138 1992-1995, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Reports 4-101 -- 4-123 1993-1996, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Reports 4-124 -- 4-126 1994-1994 (Box 8)
    [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2031 ]
  - Reports 5-101 -- 5-141 1994-1998, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Reports 96-101 -- 96-145 1995-1998, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Reports 97-101 -- 97-139 1996-2002, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Reports 98-101 -- 98-123 1997-2001, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Reports 99-101 -- 99-906 1998-2001, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Reports 00-101 -- 00-143 1999-2002, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Reports 01-101 -- 01-165 2000-2003, 7 folders (Box 9)
  - Reports 02-101 -- 02-900 2001-2003, 8 folders (Box 9)
  - Reports 03-101 -- 03-161 2002-2004, 8 folders (Box 10)
    [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2034 ]
  - Year end summary audit hours 1983-1999 (Box 10)
    [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2033 ]
- External audits
  The External Audits series, 1987-2011 (1.8 linear feet) contain records related to the audits conducted for the University by external auditing firms. There are records relating to audits of Ernst & Whinney and its successor firm, Ernst & Young between 1987 and 1996. Additionally, records and reports of audits required by the US Office of Management and Budget (OMB) Circular A-133 are present. These reports were required beginning in 1990. The paper collection of OMB reports documents the reports from 1992 to 2005. The reports from the most recent eight years are posted on the U-M Financial Operations website: http://www.finance.umich.edu/finops/reporting/annualreports. Archival versions of this page beginning in May 2012 are available in the University Web Archives http://bentley.umich.edu/dchome/webarchives/index.php.
  - Ernst & Whinney / Ernst & Young 1987-1996
    - Ernst & Whinney 1988-1989 (Box 10)
      [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2033 ]
    - Management letter and response 1987-1996, 6 folders (Box 10)
  - Office of Management and Budget (OMB) Circular A-133 Audits, FY 1991-FY 1996, 1992-1997, 5 folders (Box 10)
  - OMB Circular A-133 audits, FY 1997-FY 2004, 1992-2005, 8 folders (Box 11)
  - OMB Circular A-133 audit planning -- Financial Aid 2004-2005 (Box 11)
  - Other reports
    - Consolidated financial statements FY 2006 and 2005, 2006 (Box 11)
    - Consolidated financial statements FY 2007 and 2006, 2007 (Box 11)
    - Dearborn financial reports 2011 (Box 11)
    - External audit presentation FY 2007, 2007 (Box 11)
    - External audit presentation FY 2009, 2009 (Box 11)
    - Michigan Public Media update 2008 (Box 11)
    - PriceWaterhouseCoopers Proposal to Provide Certified Audit Services 2003 (Box 11)
    - Other audit reports issued for the year ended June 30, 2007, 2007 (Box 11)
    - Other audit reports issued for the years ended June 30, 2008-2009, 2008-2009, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Report of investments 2008-2009, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - University of Michigan Press Financial Review and Controls 2009 (Box 12)
- Standard Practice Guide (SPG)
  The final series, Standard Practice Guide, 1947-2012 (6.7 linear feet) is divided into two subseries, General, 1947-1994 (0.7 linear feet) which contains publicity materials for the SPG Online, copies of the original series of Standard Practice Bulletins that formed the basis of the original Standard Practice Guide, and a complete SPG binder from 1995. The files are arranged alphabetically. The second subseries, Amendments to SPG Provisions, 1968-2012 (6 linear feet) is arranged by SPG number. Each folder consists of the amendment history of a given policy provision. Materials in this series have been digitized and placed for safekeeping in Deep Blue, but are restricted. The digitized files exactly correspond to the materials in Boxes 13-18 and comprise about 1205 items (351.7 MB preprocessed).
  - General
    - Publicity re: SPG Online 1995-1999 (Box 12)
    - Standard Practice Bulletins 1-30 (1947-1955); Deans, Directors and Department Heads Memoranda (1949-1965) and Administration Building Instructions (1948-1949) (Box 12)
    - Standard Practice Guide circa July 1994, 5 folders (Box 12)
  - Amendments to SPG provisions
    (BHL deposit ID 2014116_0001)
    - Introduction and provisions 201.01-201.34-01, 44 folders, .ZIP file (Box 13)
    - Provisions 201.35-201.79, 55 folders, .ZIP file (Box 14)
    - Provisions 201.80-501.1, 54 folders, .ZIP file) (Box 15)
    - Provisions 501.2-1-514.04, 43 folders, .ZIP file) (Box 16)
    - Provisions 515.1-601.31, 48 folders .ZIP file) (Box 17)
    - Provisions 602.1-608.1, 32 folders .ZIP file) (Box 18)
Related Materials
The Bentley Historical Library holds a separate unrestricted collection of organizational charts derived in large part from the Standard Practice Guide: the Office of University Audits University of Michigan Organizational Charts.